[Music]
we have
now calculated by a direct method you
can call it root Force although there's
some Elegance in it the O characteristic
of all the Spheres
you might wonder and you should indeed
be wondering what the order
characteristic of any manifold that we
have encountered is you know we have
encounter many other examples of
manifolds especially in the first week
you remember Taurus real projective plan
Sigma G NG and so on and so on and in
the future you might encounter other
manifold such as Le groups and so
on yet one more remark about
this um problem of um the oil
characteristic of
spheres let's take a sphere and this is
S2
okay we said partition partition means
just draw some pictures and divide a
picture into you know curves lines and
points and
faces what
about something like this
I drew two
circles on the sphere okay I drew two
circles
well it looks like beta Z how many
vertices are there well there are no
vertices right it's
zero beta one well how many edges are
there I see to see two curves one two
right and how many faces are there well
there's this face there's this face and
then there's the face on the on the rest
so we seem have three so this if we do
that you get
one
okay and that's not equal
to what we thought we discovered which
is the other characteristic of all even
Dimension spheres should be two so
what's wrong
here we got the wrong answer
we got the wrong
answer because we are
forgetting
um this
close and bless
you each of the faces when you do this
partitioning each of the cells must be
homeomorphic to the ball of the
corresponding dimension for
example well there are lots and lots of
things wrong with this partition this
partition is
illegal
yes
because the
edges what we seem to be thinking as
edges which uh look like this yeah is
not homeomorphic 2 B1 what's B1 it's a
segment it's not a segment it's a circle
not the same thing also the
faces you have a face like this
right that's one of the things that we
call the face but that's not
homeomorphic to B2 which is a this it
has a hole in it so this partitioning
So-Cal partitioning is illegal when you
partition to draw a network work you
must make sure that every vertex is a
point every Edge is topologically a
segment and every face is propos to the
this and so on and every face should be
a ball of that dimens dimension for
example you see this face is it has
corners and so on but topologically a
dis if you draw an illegal partition
illegal Network then the numbers will
come out wrong
okay now I'd like to give although all
the projects are do today I apparently
well I might as well give you some
exercise and
projects you don't have to do this if
you run out of time because I think aim
students don't sleep enough bless you
sir
um maybe whenever you hear assignment
use needs too I me somebody's have the
same property but
these facts are very useful to know so I
just take them and you can either prove
them for yourselves submit them as
projects or you can believe them or you
can come to me and I'll show you how to
do them okay so
first project correct result is that for
any
manifolds manifolds M1 and M2 of the
same dimension
Dimension let's call the dimension
M what happens you might wonder when you
take the connected sum of M1 and M2 do
you remember this funny symbol from the
first week connected sum you can have
two manifolds of the same D Dimension
and you can just pipe them together if
you like yeah well it turns out that
this is quite easy
to a good approximation it is the sum of
the order characteristics but not quite
you have to have the correction and the
correction is minus the order
characteristic of s m minus one one
dimension down and we know what those
are depending on M we have the answers
already and then
minus - one M * 2 you might guess where
this two comes from there's some ball
involved and you are removing those
bolts and so on anyway this is the
formula if you want to calculate the oil
characteristic of the connected sum or
surgery of two manifolds then you can
write it down in terms of the each um
individual component okay not component
but half okay so that's one
also you can prove that first also by
direct calculation or direct picture you
can check that the o characteristic for
a two dimensional Taurus T2 is equal to
zero and that toil characteristic for
the what did
you call this uh space real projective
plane turn that be if you do the um just
picture drawing
one if you know these two things Taurus
and the projected plane well you can
calculate in principle the oil
characteristics of all the sigma GS and
all the nggs because Sigma GS and nggs
are just connected sums of to and real
projected
ples and
hence using the that additive addition
formula and
the starting points of the
induction you should be able to prove
easily
that I write too hard on the Blackboard
it doesn't erase
nicely but if I don't write hard enough
people in the back cannot see so it's
difficult and hence that the order
characteristic of Sigma G is quite this
is quite famous 2 - 2 G you find this
number coming up in many areas of
mathematics and what is not so widely
known is a to characteristic of all the
nonorientable surfaces which you can get
by um connected suming RPS is equal to
2us
G you should check by the way that these
make sense when G is 1 that's just a
Taurus so it should give you zero when G
is one which it does when G is 1 what's
N1 it's the project plan itself so that
should give you one which it also does
okay so in this exercise or the project
what's interesting is this statement
this formula is interesting and you can
prove it easily by drawing a
picture you have to look at the picture
of the connected Su and then somehow
draw a network on it which makes clear
the dependence on the oil characteristic
one piece and the other piece and then
what's happening in
between and also interest is those two
for that's easy to do by drawing a
diagram again and the rest from here to
here that's just an algebraic deduction
there's no grain work in it anybody can
do it okay another
exercise but I'd like to see think of
these two projects as part of the same
project let's prove also please prove
rather that for manifolds
again M1 and
M2 but this time not necessarily of the
same Dimension they can be of any
Dimension they could be of the same
Dimension but they don't have to not
necessarily of the same
Dimension no dimensional restriction you
might wonder what's the next thing you
wonder you can you have a formula for
the the sum of
manifolds you should have a formula
for
huh we are calculating the oil
characteristic for various operations we
wanted to know what happens to the
characteristic when you add manifolds
what's next okay when you multiply
manifolds
exactly so we want to find out what the
oil characteristic is of the product of
manles in terms of the o characteristics
of each and this mass is very easy it
turns out to be the oil characteristic
times the other oil
characteristic okay maybe you can write
it times so the oil
characteristic is if you like a
homomorphism or the isomorphism and
multiplication once you know
this and you know the oil characteristic
of a
circle you should be able to deduce
easily that the other characteristic of
Taurus in any Dimension is equal to
zero tremendously easy exercise and
deduction from here to
here okay we are about to
have the yellow card
as I
said if you are looking for some other
projects to do assignments to do those
two will be a very good
one but if you are already too tired
because it's the third week um and you'd
rather take it easy eating ice cream and
so on don't bother but these two things
are very useful to know and you should
have them your records okay
yes huh when I don't know um well
officially all the assignments are du
this evening but okay you can you can
give them to us maybe tomorrow or the
day after tomorrow you know but you have
other assignments so don't lose sleep I
know that you like to sleep only 4 hours
at night but like Napoleon but you know
you should sleep a little more and don't
worry too much you have already done lot
of work
okay okay after all this we shall now
come to the main result of this
chapter and like many results main
results it's attached to names of great
mathematicians one of them is quare you
should know this name if you have not
heard it before um one of the most
influential mathematicians of all time
he lived around the turn of the 20th
century from the um latter half of the
19th century to the beginning of the
20th century HRI P his cousin was raymon
P the president of the French Republic
but this is really the more famous One
and this theorem that I'm about to state
was proved by discovered by Pon in the
two dimensional case in
1881 and then hind hop a
nice Swiss m ician proved it in general
dimension in
1926 so for this reason it's sometimes
called a h theorem theorem says the
following suppose that you have a closed
orientable
manifold closed
then for
any Vector field for every sorry I think
it's every Vector
field V on
M we have that the familiar number index
of V at X where X sums over or the
equilibria is equal to a beautiful
answer we say that this number does not
depend on the choice of the vector field
it depends only on information
concerning M and we raised the question
about 20 30 minutes ago can we write it
down directly in terms of the
information about M the answer is yes it
is equal to the oil characteristic of n
beautiful
results in
particular we
see that you see when we defined M
Kai we made lots of choices you know DEC
composition or partitioning into this
form or this form depending on who's
drawing the picture beta 0 beta 1 beta 2
all those numbers changed but we are
claiming that o characteristic does not
depend on the way you partition this
proves it
because the right hand side seems to be
defined in terms of some picture we've
drawn Network we've drawn but the left
hand side knows nothing about what
network we're drawing you see each time
you have a vector field we can calculate
this so left hand side obviously does
not depend on any network of any kind so
this must be independent of the choices
we have made but we can read the
equation backwards if you want to show
that this number does not depend on the
vector field we look at this and say oh
if that's true the right hand side
depends on the on the network that we
have drawn there's no mention Vector
field so clearly this is independent of
the choice of the vector field and so
anyway so this is one conclusion we can
immediately see that the OA
characteristic is well
defined well defined means that you
don't get different answers depending on
different pictures we draw
independently this is e as you know of
how we
partition or how we
Network how we partition
M
into what
network that was an issue a problem that
was left over
from definition of the order
characteristic itself which is
definition 13 okay
okay P
theor we shall finish this class by
proving that theorem which is
not in fact too
difficult though the theorem is not
difficult to prove it has many many
applications you might remember that bra
fix Point theorem had many applications
this has almost as
many
which makes me comment that the
usefulness and even the beauty of a
mathematical result does not depend
really so much on its difficulty some
people believe that more difficult the
result the better it is but that's not
true really the best kind of results the
most useful kind are easy ones that have
many applications so I hope that in your
careers you'll be looking for easy
mathematics but which are useful useful
and so on
proof um we will do this
proof in dimension
two okay
now you see that the picture that I'm
drawing is very easily generalizable so
I'm going to do it in dimension two in
order to keep it simple but it's easy to
rewrite this in any dimension
all the other dimensions
are the same so other
dimensions uh
analogous you just follow your
notes
okay how do we do this first please
remember that when we are calculating
the left hand side from now on I should
call left hand side this number this sum
right hand side this number the other
characteristic please recall that this
left hand side we already know does not
depend on the choice of v in other words
we can calculate this left hand side by
choosing any V we
like in that case let's not choose a
complicated V Let's choose a very simple
V yeah but not so simple that um the all
the equilibria degenerate we have to
make sure that equilibria very nicely
behaved they generic so here is the V
that we shall choose and we shall prove
that result for that V so first by
corally 12 and the left hand
side the abbreviation is LHS left hand
side it's quite common and because left
hand side is very long to right you
often write LHS um
it's not large Hardon something or other
um can
be
calculated using
any any V we
like okay so we shall take the following
V first let's on M our surface draw a
network okay and we shall draw a network
which might look like this which might
look like this which might look like
this like that and then which might look
like this okay and so on we draw some
Network okay
next I'm going to copy this network
excuse me this is supposed to be the
same picture as this picture so let me
draw the same picture or what I think
should look like the same
picture see if I draw a very complicated
picture I cannot draw the same picture
again so
it's I think maybe I should start some
here yeah this looks a bit more like the
same picture um I hope this looks like
the same picture to everyone does it
look like the same picture well almost
okay now draw a network
and place the following
objects at
each
vertex a source of a vector field you
remember what the source is it's the
equilibrium where the flow is coming out
of at
each meat Edge that is the mid point of
the edge please put the sdle you
remember what the saddle is that's the
place an equilibrium where the flow is
coming in One Direction but going out in
the other direction yeah and finally at
each mid face that is the midpoint of
each
face a
syn okay syn is the point equilibrium
where all the floor is coming
in well what does that become
let's draw these give them colors Source
will be yellow and and
saddle would
be red I'm not choosing the colors very
carefully I'm sorry they might be some
better color coding scheme for example
you might have green yellow red like the
um lights of a traffic light or as they
say in South Africa a robot anyway so
those are the colors okay so let's see
at each vertex I put the source in other
words this water if you like is coming
out of each of these
points okay and in the middle of each
face that's to the
sinks it's going down at those
points okay I'm not going to draw
everywhere and then at the middle of
each vert each Edge I put a saddle so
Saddles are indicated by by Red crosses
like
this and what we do
is
then feel the rest of the
picture
picture with a suitable
flow flow the vector fi what do I mean
you know it's not too difficult to see
what's going to happen for example let's
look at this Edge there's a source the
water is coming out from here and
there's a source water is coming out of
here so the water must be going this way
but that's a
saddle which means that if the water is
coming in in this direction it must be
going out in the other direction so that
it must go out like this you know what
I'm
doing but that's lucky because this is a
sink water should be going into this
similarly here water should be coming
out of the sources
but in the middle there's a saddow so
water goes out in this
direction and here similar you get that
kind of picture you get that kind of
picture well having completed this part
what do you think will the flow of the
water in this region look like well it's
clear water goes like this and it flows
like this and in the middle it flows
straight so we have now filled this part
of the picture in a pretty much unique
way and similarly for any
other part of the picture so this is a
sink so it's squirting out water in all
directions but that's a sdle this is a
so water should come out here because
it's going in this direction and because
towards this Shadow it's going in it
should come out in this direction and
here therefore I can feel the picture
like this here I can feel the picture
like this this here I can feel the
picture like this and as for here yes
you guessed I can feel the picture like
this and so on so you can feel the flow
everywhere is that okay so this
way given any
network I can draw a vector
field giving any network I can draw a
vector field and we are saying let's use
that particular Vector field to
calculate the index
I know that that number we get at the
end is independent of the choice of the
vector field so that is this number and
we shall see if that number has anything
to do with the oiler
characteristic it turns out that it
does because
let's recall X example
nine do you remember what indices
sources and sinks have in dimension
two
huh they contribute what was the index
plus or minus one for Source zero for
syn plus yeah so for Saddles it was Zero
for source and syn uh sorry not zero
actually minus one sad minus
one SN and Source plus two Plus+ one so
SN source source Ling contribute plus
one
while
Saddles
contribute minus one
each on two dimensional
in dimension two um okay on two
dimensional
surface you should look back at the
calculation of example 9 and check this
so what do we
have the left hand side always of that F
we have to add up all the indices with
plus and minuses well how many how
many syns are there sorry how many
sources are there exactly as many as the
number of
vertices right so this is of course the
number of vertices but also it's number
of
sources and they contribute plus
one okay that's the index contributed by
each of the
sources okay okay
plus how many um Saddles are
there well there are exactly as many
Saddles as the number of
edges that's beta 2 each saddle
contributes minus one that's the
index over the
sdle so I have to add add that to the
previous result and finally
how many sinks are
[Applause]
there as many as their their faces but
that's beta 2 and each sync contributes
what's the index it contributes plus
one so I have to add that to the
previous
result and if you look at what we get
it's beta 0 minus beta 1 plus beta 2
that's exactly the oil characteristic
which is the right hand side and the
proof nice I hope that you understand
the logic of this um
calculation okay so we have now approved
thank you and this is the end um good
timing in fact not good timing it's too
too long oh that's you should have
something in Red so that you can it's
really red so we have now proved p h and
we shall see tomorrow when we start that
this can be used in again two different
ways this great theorem which says left
hand side equals right hand side can be
used in the following ways way number
one you can say oh we don't know what
the left hand side is but we know what
the right hand side is so let's find out
what left is from the right that's one
way to do it another way is oh we don't
know what the right hand side is but we
know what the left hand side is so we
let's figure out right from left can
work in both ways and we'll see many
examples
tomorrow